我们来谈谈内核堆
let's talk about kernel heap
以及slab分配器的工作原理
and how slab allocators work
我们在之前的模块中花了很多时间讨论堆
now we've spent a lot of time talking about the heap in prior modules
但我们讨论的都是用户空间的堆
but everything we've talked about has been specific to userland heap
准确的说
and beyond that
是特定于glibc实现版本的，用户空间的堆
it's been specific to glibc's implementation of a userland heap
这是许多Linux系统的通常情况
now that is the common case for a lot of Linux systems
所以讨论它是有意义的
so it makes sense to talk about this
我们有一整个模块讲的tcache
we had a whole module dedicated to tcache
它是出于性能优化的缓存层
which is like the performance optimization caching layer
大量的动态内存请求，可通过它得到满足
that a lot of dynamic memory requests can be satisfied via
所以它绝对是值得讨论和探索的
and so it's definitely worth talking about and exploring how that works
如果tcache满足不了的话
now if something can't be satisfied by the tcache
就会深入更大的堆
it goes into kind of the greater heap
这里就要说到bins了
and that's where we have to deal with this concept of bins
有unsorted bin
we have the unsorted bin
有large bins、small bins和fast bins
we have the large bins the small bins the fast bins
空闲chunk会在这些bins中传递
and we see that free chunks kind of move between these different bins
这取决于
depending upon what's going on
可用的动态内存
in as far as dynamic memory that is available
和请求的动态内存
in what is being requested in dynamic memory
Linux内核使用完全不同的实现
but the Linux kernel uses a completely different implementation
我想问的一个问题是。为什么？
and one of the questions that I mean I certainly ask is why
为什么Linux内核需要一个完全不同的堆
why does the Linux kernel need an entirely different heap
我们来想想内核是怎么工作的
well let's think about how the kernel works
以及内核的独特约束
and kind of the unique constraints of the kernel
首先内核在意性能
so above all the kernel cares about performance
用户空间程序也关心性能
userland cares about performance as well
但两者的影响是不能相提并论的
but there's a very different impact of a slow path in user land versus a slow path in the kernel
如果我写一些慢的用户空间程序
if I write some slow user land program
唯一慢的是我的用户空间程序
the only thing that's slow is my user land program
如果内核的代码很慢
now if the kernel has a slow code path
这会减慢系统上的每个程序
that slows down every program on the system
原因是
and the reason for that is because
程序只有依赖内核，才能完成有意义的工作
every program relies on the kernel to get any type of like real work done
现在我们来想想
now let's think about
用户空间glibc堆实现中的一些操作
some of the operations or actions that occur inside the Userland glibc heap implementation
用户空间堆花了很多时间读写元数据
well the user land heap spends a decent amount of time reading and writing metadata
比如prev_size、size
like previous size or the size
large bins用的fd_nextsize、bk_nextsize
next pointers previous pointers for large bins
要额外的指针来索引到
there's additional pointers to try and navigate to free chunks
堆管理的空闲chunk
that are being tracked by the heap
对于这些空闲chunk
and on the topic of these free chunks
glibc实现的堆
the glibc implementation of the heap
花了不少时间
spends a decent amount of time
在这些不同bins之间转移空闲chunk
moving free chunks between all of these different bins
unsorted bin中的某个chunk
I may have something in the unsorted bin
后面可能要转移到large bin中
then needs to go to the large bin
这需要额外的工作
right and there is additional work that needs to occur
要额外的工作
it's additional cycles that are occurring
来计算或记录它
in order to kind of do that accounting or track that
如果我尝试malloc些东西会发生什么
or what happens if I try malloc something
假设有一个够大的空闲chunk
and there is a free chunk that is large enough
但有点太大了（超过了请求大小）
but it's a little bit too large
glibc堆实现
well the glibc heap implementation
可能会将它切成两份
may break that chunk in two
然后得整理那个剩下的
and then have to sort the second half of the original chunk
这又要做更多的工作
again that's more work that is being done
换一个堆的实现可能可以避免它
that maybe a different implementation of the heap could otherwise avoid
另外，内核是一直运行的
additionally the kernel essentially runs forever
只要系统启动，内核就在运行
because the kernel runs as long as the system is up
它不像用户空间程序
it isn't like a user land program
可以启动，停止，重启它
where we can start it up stop it and then restart it
重启内核等同于重启电脑
restarting the kernel is essentially rebooting your computer
所以内核必须高效利用内存
so the kernel has to be memory efficient
不能丢失内存或泄漏内存
it can't lose track of memory or have memory leaks
我们讨论了可能会用到的额外内存
now we already talked about the additional memory that's kind of used potentially
用来在用户空间堆中存储元数据的
from storing metadata in the user land heap representation
能避免的话
well if we can avoid that
就节省了空间
that is a space savings
我们可以做的另一件事
the additional thing that we can do
是
is something that
讨论用户空间堆时，没细讲到的
we didn't really talk about in detail talking about the user land heap
就是glibc堆实现容易产生内存碎片
but the glibc heap implementation is susceptible to memory fragmentation
我说的内存碎片是什么意思
what do I mean when I say memory fragmentation
我们想一下幻灯片右边的三行代码
well let's consider the three lines of code on the right hand side of this slide
malloc 0x80字节
we malloc hex 80 bytes
然后释放这0x80字节
we then free those hex 80 bytes
再malloc 0x60字节
then we malloc Hex 60 bytes
这里我们忽略tcache
now let's ignore the tcache right now
想一下堆的深处发生了什么
and just think about what goes on kind of deeper into the heap
因为这是一个人为的例子
because this is a contrived example
我们忽略tcache
and so we're going to ignore tcache here
很有可能
well there's a reasonable chance
在第二次malloc 0x60字节时
that the second malloc of hex 60 bytes
会返回上行代码释放的chunk
will be satisfied by the free chunk that we just freed in the line above
这样做
now by doing so
我们会取到较大的那个chunk
we take the larger chunk
我们把空闲chunk掰成两份
and we break it into two pieces
返回0x60字节的chunk
and we return the allocation of hex 60
最后剩下一个空闲的0x20字节的chunk
and we'll end up with a unused chunk of size hex 20
如果我一直持续这个操作
now if I were to like repeat this operation here
这3行代码
these three 3 lines of code
把它放入while循环或for循环中
throw it in a while loop or in a for loop
运行好几次
you know and ran it several several times
我们会看到，每次执行
what we would see is every iteration of this
就创建一个代码不用的0x20字节的chunk
is creating one of these hex 20 chunks that the code isn't using
运行的代码一直不需要，不用这0x20字节的chunk
at no point does the code that is actually running need or use this hex 20 size chunk
所以我们创造了很多无用的0x20字节大小的chunk
and so we're creating all of these hex 20 size chunks that serve no purpose
这显然是一个刻意的例子
now this is a contrived example obviously
你不会让它在死循环中运行
that you wouldn't want to run this in an infinite loop
但是从内核的角度来看
however from the kernel's perspective
这一系列分配和释放的发生是完全合理的
it's totally plausible for this series of allocations and frees to occur
内核需要一直运行
and the kernel needs to run indefinitely
所以这些没用的小chunk
so these little kind of unused chunks that create
按这种方式创建的
that get created from this pattern
会随着时间累积
would build up over time
导致内存碎片化，基本无法使用
and result in fragmented memory that is essentially useless
这当然是内核想要避免的
and that is certainly something that the kernel wants to avoid
Linux内核的堆实现
the Linux kernel's heap implementation
依赖于slab分配器
relies on something that's known as a slab allocator
slab这个词在这个领域有重叠
now the term slab is overloaded within this domain
所以它有2个意思
so there are two usages of the word slab
如果是小写slab
slab if it is lowercase
就是指一块连续的内存区
implies a contiguous region of memory
一块内存
a slab of memory
或者指块内存分配器
or a slab allocator
使用slab概念的分配器
an allocator that uses this concept of slabs
但如果是全大写的SLAB
however if the word slab is all capitalized
这指一种特定的slab分配器实现
this refers to a specific implementation of a generic slab allocator
Linux使用过三种不同的slab分配器实现
now there's three different implementations of slab allocators that have been used in Linux
第一个是SLOB
the first is SLOB
它是"简单一列内存块"的首字母缩写
which is an acronym for a Simple List Of Blocks
我这里写着已弃用
I list this is deprecated
然而，它在内存受限的环境中仍有使用
however it does still see some use in memory constrained environments
比如在嵌入式系统中
so like on embedded systems
可能有SLOB的slab分配器实现
there may be a SLOB implementation of a slab allocator
还有SLAB的slab分配器实现
there is also the SLAB implementation of a slab allocator
就是这里与slab重复了
this is where that kind of redundant use of the word slab
让人有点困惑
can get a little confusing
Linux源代码允许
the Linux source code does allow
编译时选择SLAB库实现
for compiling with this SLAB implementation
但它不是默认选项，已经很久不是了
however it is no longer default and hasn't been for quite some time
linux的默认slab分配器实现
the default kind of Linux kernel implementation of a slab allocator
叫SLUB
is known as SLUB
U表示非队列的
which is an acronym for an unqueued slab allocator
这张幻灯片后
right and so everything past this slide
slab分配器指的都是的SLUB
will be referring to the SLUB implementation of a slab allocator
内核的堆实现
the kernel's heap implementation
与用户空间glibc堆实现有很大的不同
differs quite a bit from what we've seen in userland with glibc's heap implementation
因为实现方式不同
and since the implementation is quite different
所以用了不同的术语
we have different terminology that is used
在讨论slab分配器时说chunk是不准确的
it would be technically incorrect to refer to chunks when talking about a slab allocator
这里我们经常用到的术语有
so the terms that we're going to kind of be throwing around here
首先cache
first is cache
当我们讨论这些分配器时，cache是最高级别的概念
now a cache is kind of the highest level concept when we're talking about these allocators
一个cache管理一个指定大小内存
a cache is created for a specific size
所以内核分配器中用到了很多cache
so there's many different caches that are used within the kernels allocator
有管理256B对象的cache
there's a cache for 256 byte objects
有管理512B对象的cache
there's a cache for 512 byte objects
如果堆要管理一些特定大小的内存
if there is some specific size that needs to be managed by the heap
就会创建一个cache，管理该大小内存
a cache is created specific to that size
cache管理一种叫做slab的东西
now caches manage something called slabs
这是slab分配器名字的由来
and this is where the generic term of slab allocator comes from
一个slab是一块连续的内存
a slab is a continuous region of memory
它可以占一个或多个内存页
that can be one or more pages in size
这取决于要管理的资源有多大
it kind of depends on what is being managed to source how large is a slab
slab由一连串slot组成
and these slabs consist of a series of slots
slot是slab中的内存区域
where the slot is a region of memory within the slab
slot的大小是cache管理的大小
that is the size being managed by the cache
如果我们有一个cache管理256B
so if we have a 256 byte cache
那在slab中的slot的大小就是256B
then these slots that are on the slab will be 256 bytes in size
slot中装着对象
now slots can contain objects
如果slot的大小是256B
so if the slot is the region of memory that is 256 bytes in size
那malloc发生时，这里在内核中是kmalloc
what happens when a malloc occurs or kmalloc in the case of the kernel
返回的指针
is the pointer that is returned
指向某个可用的空闲slot
is a pointer to one of these available slots
当这个slot被使用后
and once that available slot is being used
我们会说那个slot中包含一个对象或内核对象
we would say that that slot contains an object or a kernel object
我们在这里看到
and so we see here
调用kmalloc或其它方式申请内存后，返回的指针
that a pointer that was returned from calling kmalloc or somehow getting an allocation
是一个指向slab内存中的一个指针
would be a pointer into the region of memory of the slab
指向的slot现在装着一个对象
and specifically pointing to a slot that now contains an object
使用这种slab分配器方法的好处之一是
now one of the kind of benefits of using this slab allocator approach
对象初始化之后
is that once objects are initialized
初始化的数据，只要有可能，就可重用
that initialized data can be reused when possible
回想一下glibc堆是如何实现的
so if we think about how the glibc heap implementation worked
我们调用malloc，然后调用free
we called malloc and then free
然后再malloc
and then malloc again
无法保证返回内存中的值是多少
we have no guarantee about the values of the memory that is returned to us
然而，在这个slab实现中
however with this slab implementation
如果为特定对象类型专门创建了cache
if a cache is created for a specific object type
该对象有专门的数据结构
for a specific data structure
可能有些静态值
and there are kind of static values
然后，当所有slot都用该静态值初始化后
then once all of the slots have been initialized with that static value
就可以假定这个数据在返回slot时就存在了
we can assume that that data is already there when we obtain the allocation
因为这些内存的唯一用途
because the only thing that these regions or memory are being used for
就是装该数据结构
are those specific data structures
右边的示意图
so the diagram on the right
是偏概念性，而非技术细节
is more conceptual than it is technical
一个更准确的内核堆实现示意图
a more technically accurate representation of the kernel heap implementation
在这里
is shown here
这里我们展示了
where we are specifically calling out
实际用到的数据结构
the actual data structures that are used
最高级别的数据结构是kmem_cache
so the highest level data structure is the kmem_cache
有一个kmem_cache管理256B对象
and so there's a kmem_cache for 256 byte objects
有一个kmem_cache管理512B对象
there's a kmem_cache for 512 byte objects right
所以kmem_cache在概念上和我们的cache是相同的
and so the kmem_cache is conceptually the same thing as our cache
但是在cache实现中
however in the caches implementation
它还使用了另外两种数据结构
it uses these two other data structures
一个是kmem_cache_cpu
it has the kmem_cache_cpu
一个是kmem_cache_node
and it has this kmem_cache_node
我们可以像这样分开考虑
now we can think about this split here as follows
左边的数据结构用于表示
the data structures on the left here are represented to kind of
被某个cpu使用的slab
the working set or the working slab that is in use for a specific CPU
右边的数据结构
where the data structures on the right here
记录着未被CPU使用的slab
contain information about slabs that are not being used by the current CPU
为什么要做这样的区分
so why why do we have this this kind of division
这与glibc堆中使用的tcache类似
well this is very similar to what we have with tcache in the glibc heap
tcache表示线程本地存储
tcache represented thread local storage
获取这里的chunk
there are allocations that the thread
线程可以不阻塞，不用等待底层堆
can obtain without having to kind of block and wait for the greater heap
如果有多个线程试图malloc
if there are multiple threads that are trying to malloc something
我们不希望所有这些线程都在相互等待
we don't want to have all of these threads waiting on each other
这里也是类似的概念
it's a similar idea here
在内核堆实现中
with the kernel heap implementation
不对线程上锁
except instead of locking on a thread
我们处于特定于CPU的预留级别
we are on a CPU specific kind of reservation level
左边的数据结构
so the data structures on the left hand side
是为当前cpu预留的
are what the current CPU has reserved
可以直接访问它，从这里获取内存
and it can access and allocate from
不用担心与其他cpu争
without worrying about having contention with other CPUs
对于每个cache
so for every cache
对于每个CPU
for every CPU
有一个激活的使用中的slab
there is an active working slab
有这么一个CPU正在与之交互的工作集
there's this working set that the CPU is interacting with
就是我们看到的绿色部分
that's what we see here in green
但当需要新的slab时
but when a new slab is needed
可以放partial slab进去
partial slabs can be swapped in
如果我们考虑一下
so like if we consider
我们在左边有这个工作集
we have this working set over here on the left hand side
当所有slot都满了
what happens when all of the slots are full
我们又要申请一个对象时
and we need to allocate another object
kmem_cache来到右边
well the kmem_cache can go over to the right hand side
找到一个有空闲slot的slab
find a slab that has open slots
该slab中可能有些slot已经分配出去了
it may have some slots allocated
但它要有空闲的slot
but it should have some open or free slots
它可以将那个slab，或说内存
and it can kind of claim ownership of that slab or that region of memory
当作它要用的新工作集
as its new working set that it is going to use
partial slabs记录在链表中
now partial slabs are tracked in the linked list
由kmem_cache_node中的nr_partial指针记录
they are in this nr_partial pointer in the kmem_cache_node
完整的slab实际上不会记录
full slabs actually aren't tracked at all
除非内核被专门编译为这样做
unless the kernel is compiled specifically to do so
所以当一块slab全被分配出去时
so when we fully allocate a kind of backing region of memory
内核可以不管它
we the kernel can just forget about
因为内核相信
because the kernel trusts
内核代码能正确地管理它
that kernel code will manage that properly
它会在某刻释放出来
at some point it will be freed
当它被释放后，才需要再次记录它
and when this freed is when it needs to be tracked again
所以如果有一个slab全部都分配出去
and so if we have a slab that is fully allocated
我们不知道它在哪里
we don't even know where it is
内核并不关心
the kernel doesn't care
但是一旦其中一个对象被释放
but as soon as one of those objects are freed
它就变成了一个部分分配的slab
it becomes a partially allocated slab
它就是一个partial slab了
it's a partial slab
在它的第一个对象被释放时
and it is at the time of when the first object is freed
这个slab将被添加到右边的元数据中
that that slab will be added to the metadata over on the right hand side
因为它至少有一个空闲slot
because suddenly it at least has one slot
所以它可以用在工作集中
and so it could be used in a working set
不会记录全分配出去的slab的位置
there are no tracking of full slabs
除非它被显式编译成这样做
unless it's explicitly compiled to do so
堆相关内容很多
now that was a lot of components to show in a single slide
但幸运的是，就我们的题目而言
but fortunately for the challenges
就我们在这个模块要探索的概念而言
kind of concepts that we're exploring in this module
我们只需关注支撑slab的内存
we really only need to focus on the memory that is backing the slab
以及slab中的slots
as well as the slots that exist within that region of memory
我们首先要看的是
what we're primarily going to be looking at is
对象是如何在slab的slots中分配的
how the objects are allocated on the slab in those slots
以及这些slots之间的关联
and how those slots relate to each other
专注于slab内存
so focusing on the slab's memory
我们可以把它想象成一个连续的内存区域
we can think of this as a contiguous region of memory
它由固定大小的slot组成
that's made up of fixed size slots
要么是空闲可分配的
that are either free and available for allocation
要么是已经分配给该大小的内核对象了
or the slot currently contains some kernel object of that size
slab上的所有slot都是大小固定的
recall that all slots on a slab are a fixed size
因为一个slab支持一种特定的cache
because that slab is supporting a specific cache
一个cache中的所有内容都是大小固定的
and everything from one cache has a fixed size
这样分配的对象不需要元数据，避免内存浪费
no space is wasted on metadata for allocated objects
那么当我们释放一个对象时会发生什么呢
so what happens when we free an object
这和tcache类似
well very similar to tcache
释放的对象被压入单链表
freed objects are pushed onto a singly linked list
SLUB实现的slab分配器中
for the SLUB implementation of the slab allocator
这个空闲链表是一个单链表
this free list is a singly linked list
和我们在tcache中看到的非常相似
very similar to what we see in tcache
这里空闲链表中有一个slot
so here there is one slot on the free list
它的next指针为空
and the next pointer is null
那么如果我们释放这个第4个slot会发生什么呢
so what would happen if we were to free this 4th slot
这个slot里面有个内核对象
which currently contains a kernel object
和我们平常讨论单链表时
well we would do the same thing that we normally do
做的一样
when we're talking about singly linked lists
我们会把它作为空闲链表的头节点
we would push this onto the head of the free list
然后更新next指针
and then update the next pointer
事实就是如此
and that's exactly what happens
如果我们释放了第四个slot
if we were to free this fourth slot
空闲列表的头指针现在指向第四个slot
the freelist head pointer now points to the fourth slot
往第四个slot中放了一个next指针，指向第三个slot
and a next pointer is placed inside the fourth slot that points to the third slot
然后第三个slot的next指针为空
and then the next pointer of the third slot is null
表示链表结束
indicating the end of the linked list
如果我们要分配一个对象
if we were to then allocate an object
我们只需取出空闲列表的头节点
we would simply pull from the head of the free list
这将返回第四个slot
and that would return the fourth slot
我们之后会把内核对象放在那里
where we would place that kernel object
我们会更新空闲列表的头指针，为头节点的next
we would update the head of the free list to be head next
于是下次返回的空闲列表的头节点
and so the head of the free list returns
将是这个第三个slot
to become that third slot
考虑这个链表时，有一个重要的区别
one important difference to be aware of when thinking about this linked list
就是next指针的位置
is the location of the next pointer
tcache中单链表
when we took a look at tcaches single linked list
的next指针位于被释放内存的起始位置
the next pointers were located at the beginning of the freed allocation
而在内核堆中
with the kernel heap
next指针位于释放slot的中间位置
the next pointer is located midway through the freed slot
在这个例子中
so in this example
我们使用的slot的大小是0x100B，即256B
we're working with slots of size hex 100 bytes or 256 bytes
next指针位于开头偏移0x80B处
so the next pointer would be offset 128 bytes or hex 80 bytes
即slot开头偏移128B处
from the beginning of the free slot
这样做是为了防止
this is done to hopefully prevent
小的越界写入损坏next指针
the scenario where a small out of bounds write would corrupt the next pointer
可以通过kmem_cache_create函数创建cache
caches can be created via the kmem_cache_create function
你可能想为一个内核对象创建专门的cache
now you may want to create a dedicated cache for a kernel object
因为你需要分配大量这样的对象
because you know you're going to suddenly be needing to allocate a large number of these objects
你想要有一定的性能属性
and you want to have certain performance characteristics
因此你为该特定的内核对象大小设置专用cache
and so you'll find more reliability by having a dedicated cache for that specific kernel objects size
它也可以用来
it can also be used to
将这些对象与在通用cache中找到的对象隔离开来
isolate those objects from the objects that are found on the general purpose cache
要从一个专用cache中分配内存
now in order to allocate from a specific cache
要使用kmem_cache_alloc函数
you use the kmem_cache_alloc function
这能让你从指定cache中获取一个对象
this allows you to specify the cache from which you are obtaining an object from
因为cache有一个已知的大小
since caches have a known size
所以你不用指定要获取的对象的大小
you actually do not specify the size of the object you are trying to obtain
因为它已经被cache定义了
because it's already defined by the cache itself
然而，常见的情况是使用kmalloc
the common case however is to use kmalloc
它用于常规内核堆分配
which is used for general kernel allocations
如果我们看一下这里的函数声明
and if we look at the function signature here
kmalloc与用户空间的malloc非常相似
kmalloc is very similar to userland malloc
kmalloc接受一个size和flags参数
kmalloc takes a size as well as a flags parameter
kmalloc会
now what kmalloc does
会使用通用cache
is it will use the general purpose caches
它会根据请求的大小选择一个合适的
and it will choose which one is appropriate based upon the requested size
这些通用cache有一个命名约定
now these general purpose caches have a naming convention
比如kmalloc-8k
such as kmalloc-8k
其中8K是该cache提供的slot的大小
where 8K is the size of the slot that is offered by that cache
所以有kmalloc-256
so there is a kmalloc-256
kmalloc-512
there's a kmalloc-512
kmalloc-多种slot大小
there's a kmalloc for a large number of slot sizes
当你调用kmalloc
and when you call kmalloc in the general sense here
它会使用这些通用cache中的一个
it's going to use one of these general purpose caches
来完成分配请求
to fulfill that allocation request
最近增加的一个flag
now one of the more recent additions
GFP_KERNEL_ACCOUNT标志
is the addition of the GFP_KERNEL_ACCOUNT flag
这是专门用来标记
this is used specifically to note
分配内存将放一些不一定可信的内核对象
that the allocation is going to be some kernel object that isn't necessarily trusted
比如，包含用户空间数据的内核对象
like say it's some kernel object that also contains userland data
我们会把用户空间数据复制到这个内核对象中
we're going to copy userland data into this kernel object
通过指定GFP_KERNEL_ACCOUNT
by specifying GFP_KERNEL_ACCOUNT
这些分配请求将去专门的cache中找
these allocations will go to a dedicated cache
这些专门的cache差不多镜像了通用cache
that kind of mirrors the general purpose kmalloc caches
所以不会去，比如kmalloc-8k中分配
so instead of going to for instance kmalloc-8k
而是去叫kmalloc-cg-8k的cache中分配
it would go to a cache named kmalloc-cg-8k
这就是不可信的分配可以存放的地方
and this is where these untrusted allocations can residen
这也是为了进一步分离
this is again to further separate concerns
纯粹的内核数据
data that is purely in the kernel
放入通用cache
can go into general purpose caches
可能受内核之外因素影响的数据
and data that may be influenced by factors outside of the kernel
放入kmalloc-cg系列cache
can go to this kmalloc-cg series of caches
作为收场
to wrap up
我们看一下dojo系统上一些可用的cache
let's take a look at some of the caches that are available on the dojo system
这里，我已经ssh连入dojo环境
so over here I am already ssh into the dojo
并且我已经运行了VM connect命令
and I have already ran the VM connect command
所以我在挑战题实例中的一个虚拟机上
so I am inside a VM on my challenge instance
如果我运行sudo cat /proc/slabinfo
if I were to run the command sudo cat /proc/slabinfo
我们应该能看到相当多的输出
we should see quite a bit of output here
确实如此
and we do
我们去到它的开头
we go up to the beginning of it
我们能看到slabinfo version 2.1
what we'll see here is slab info version 2.1
然后是表头信息
we then have some header information
我们看看这些输出都是什么
so let's take a look and see what this output is
第一列是cache的名称
the first column is the name of the cache
我们看到
and so we see that
有些cache以特定的内核对象命名
there are caches that are named after specific kernel objects
例如，我们有这个kheap_obj
we have for instance this kheap_obj or
或这个ip6-frags对象
this ip6-frags object
所以肯定有一些对象有专门的cache
so there are definitely objects that have dedicated caches
如果我们向下滚动
and if we were to scroll down
接近这个输出的底部
closer to the bottom of this output
我们会看到
we will see
下面是通用cache
here are the general purpose caches
我们有
so we have
例如kmalloc-8k或kmalloc-256 kmalloc-96
for instance that kmalloc-8k or kmalloc-256 kmalloc-96
这些是用于kmalloc的通用cache
these are general purpose caches that are used for kmalloc
如果只是一个常规内存分配请求
if it's just like a general allocation
我们没有指定特定的cache
we aren't specifying a specific cache
它就会用这些通用cache中的一个
it's going to use one of these kind of generic ones
如果使用了GFP_KERNEL_ACCOUNT标志
now I said if we use the GFP_KERNEL_ACCOUNT flag
那么kmalloc会使用这些cache的一个
then kmalloc will use one of these caches here
kmalloc-cg跟着大小
where it's kmalloc-cg and then a size
我们看到这些cache也存在于这个系统中
and we see these caches also exist on this system
现在我们回到最上面
now if we go back up to the top
接着看表头
let's check the header data
我们可以看到cache中存在的对象数量
we get to see the number of objects that exist within that cache
对象的大小
the size of the object
还有每个slab能装的对象数量
as well as number of objects per slab
以及每个slab占用的内存页数
and pages per slab
我们说的slab并不等同于一个内存页
as we call a slab is not necessarily equal to a page
一个slab可以占用多个连续内存页
a slab can have a backing region of memory that is multiple pages
我们可以看到第二个cache就是这种情况
and we see that is the case here on this second cache
这个9p-fcall-cache
for this 9p-fcall-cache
看起来
it looks like the objects
从这个cache返回的对象非常大
that are returned from this cache are quite large in size
大约131,000字节
about 131,000 bytes
它的每个slab上只有一个对象
and so there's one object per slab
对于这个cache，一个slab占64页
that a slab is 64 pages for this particular cache
我不知道这个内核对象是什么
I have no idea what this kernel object is
这个cache要支持的对象
that the cache is meant to support
但它显然很大
but it's clearly quite large
如果我们看一下表头的最右边
if we look over to the far right of the header data
这个绕到下一行开头了
it looks like this does wrap around
另一条我觉得很有趣的信息
the other piece of information that I find quite interesting
是slab的数量
is the number of slabs
这里的倒数第二个值
so this is going to be the second to the end value here
我们看到
and so we see right now
有些cache实际上没有slab
there's some caches that actually have zero slabs right
它们有0个对象
they have 0 objects
然后它们有0个slab
and in turn they have 0 slabs
这也说的通
which makes some sense
如果不需要用它，为啥要占用slab呢，对吧
why keep the slab around if it doesn't need to be used for anything
我们可以划到下面这里看看
and we can scroll down here and we see
有些cache有不止一个slab
well there are some caches that have more than one slab
以nfs_read_data为例
this nfs_read_data for instance
每个slab占2页
it is two pages per slab
它有4个slab
and it has four slabs
也就是说
so that means that there's eight pages
为这个nfs_read_data cache预备了8页内存
backing the data of this nfs_read_data cache
它有36个对象，每个大小为896B
it has 36 objects of 896 bytes in size
这很有趣
and so this is very interesting
这是一个很容易的，查看系统上的cache的方法
and this is an easy way to kind of see these caches on your system